all right
[Music]
most persistent industrial pollutants
like organic chlorine pesticides such as
ddpt and pcbs were banned several
decades ago and dioxin emission is
strictly regulated however we're still
exposed to these chemicals through
several Roots the major source of which
is contaminated food especially fatty
animal products such as fish meat and
milk when we eat these chemicals they
get primarily stored in our own fatty
tissue where they slowly Leach out into
our bloodstream but better in our fat
than in our brain or other vital organs
having more body fat may actually play a
protective role by sequestering the
toxins away but they can come spilling
out
when we lose weight
body weight loss increases the
concentrations of potentially toxic
pollutants in obese individuals of the
19 pollutant study they all went up 15
significantly so every study that hasn't
looked at it found increased blood
levels of toxic pollutants accompanying
weight loss whether induced by diet or
bariatric surgery increases
between 14 and 388 percent with a large
enough loss oh the more weight that's
lost the higher the pollutant levels
climb because all those chemicals store
in your fat or all those years come
spilling out the theoretical concern is
that if released into the blood at a
faster rate than they're cleared the
levels of these compounds could become
toxic causing side effects such as
sweating Headache nausea but the
opposite happened when PCB poisoned
patients were fasted
in 1979 about 2 000 people in Taiwan
were exposed via an industrial accident
that contaminated rice oil leading them
to have a higher body toxicity burden
than even long-time consumers of seafood
but after a modified fasting regimen all
16 patients they tried it on showed
improvements with some enjoying dramatic
relief of their sufferings but this was
after just a few days of fasting so they
couldn't have really lost that much body
fat and they didn't measure pcbs before
and after so it's not clear that they
were experiencing some sort of detox nor
what relevance this has for people who
haven't been acutely poisoned the
initial rise in pollutant levels in the
first year of weight loss may eventually
stabilize or fall check out what
happened in Biosphere 2 a remarkable
experiment designed to be a completely
closed ecosystem the longest sustained
period of humans isolated in a confined
environment on record but due to crop
failure as it turned into a two-year
experiment of calorie restraint they all
lost about 25 pounds in the first six
months and stabilized there and while
the levels of pcbs in a DDT metabolite
known as DDE initially went up they
appeared to start coming back down but
that initial spike is quite a jump
that's one of the reasons Health
authorities recommend women don't try to
slim down during breastfeeding right uh
for example here's a woman whose breast
milk levels jumped up after she had
fasted and lost about 20 pounds because
fat is mobilized into breast milk the
secretion of human milk is a major way
these pollutants are eliminated from the
mother's body breast is still best
regardless but you can keep your levels
lower by not going out of your way to
lose weight until after breastfeeding is
finished
what can one do to help flush the
contaminants during weight loss but one
of the reasons the pollutant levels in
the biosphere subjects eventually
dropped is because they were eating a
high fiber diet centered around fruits
whole grains beans nuts and vegetables
and we know the fiber can bind to these
pollutants and potentially flush them
out of the body so when losing weight
eating lots of whole grains may be
important to increase the elimination of
pollutants well of course cutting down
on animal fat including fish so you
don't pile on extra at the same time
what about just
some Pringles
what was the dietary intervention in
this randomized trial to decrease the
body burden of pollutants subjects were
randomized to 24 fat-free Pringles a day
or regular Pringles what why it all
started with this crazy case report of a
guy heavily contaminated by pcbs who
managed to rid himself of 90 percent by
losing weight eating potato chips made
out of the fake fat olester which
doesn't get absorbed and so appears to
pull pollutants out of the bloodstream
into the stool for elimination it works
in mice increasing the excretion of a
hexachlorbenzene 30-fold and cutting the
levels in their brains in half but in
people
the drop in PCB blood levels with the
illustrial Pringles was not
statistically significantly greater and
for some reason the LDL bad cholesterol
levels shot up 28 points in the elster
group and while Western drugs like
cholestaramine May absorb pollutants and
remove them from your system they also
may cause you to dump fat soluble
vitamins so to get the best of both
worlds losing pollution without losing
vitamins fiber-rich Foods may be our
best choice
instead of olestra supplementation to
detox why not try to not talk so much in
the first place
[Music]